Guide to the William Russell Dudley Papers SC0558
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William Russel Dudley papers
1874-1913
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Dudley, William Russel
SC0558
10.25 Linear Feet
Papers include field notes, a diary, manuscripts, articles and reprints, maps, and correspondence; most of the field notes relate to California, with occasional later annotations by other botanists. Some of the material relates to Big Basin Redwoods State Park and the Sierra Club. The diary is from a tour of the California missions from December 27, 1895 to January 7, 1896 and includes photographs. Correspondents include Michael Schuck Bebb, Frederick V. Coville, Elias Durand, Alice Eastwood, Gifford Pinchot, C. O. Thurston, Charles Frederick Millspaugh, Charles Sprague Sargent, and J. H. B. Pilkington. There is also a large correspondence file on California forest fires of 1899.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical & Historical Sketch
William Russel Dudley earned his bachelor's (1874) and master's (1876) degrees in botany at Cornell University; after graduation he pursued botanical study in Strassburg and Berlin. He taught at Cornell and Indiana University before joining the Stanford faculty in 1892. Once at Stanford, his work focused on California flora, with a special interest in the study of trees; he was instrumental in the establishment of the Big Basin Redwoods State Park.
[Reprinted from SCIENCE, N.S., Vol. XXXIV., No. 866, Pages 142- 145, August 4, 1911]
William Russel Dudley, professor of systematic botany in Stanford University, was born on a farm in North Guilford, Conll., on :iUarch 1, 1849, and died at Los Altos, Cal., on June 4, 1911. The fact that the writer has been intimately associated with Professor Dudley since the day he entered the freshman class at Cornell University, in September, 1870, will perhaps excuse the personal element in this little sketch. The word" instructor" as a technical term, describing a minor assistant to a professor, had just then been invented, and the present writer had just been appointed "instructor in botany" under Professor Albert N. Prentiss.
One day, Professor Henry T. Eddy, now of Minnesota, brought to me a tall, well-built, handsome and refined young man, older and more mature than most freshmen, and with more serious and definite purposes. Young Dudley had an intense delight in out-door things and especially in flowers and birds. He wanted to be a botanist, and had turned from old Yale, to which as a descendant of Chittendens, Griswolds and Dudleys he would naturally have gone, to new Cornell, because Cornell offered special advantages in science, and because at Cornell a good man could, if need be, pay his own way. For the rest of my stay at Cornell, Dudley was my room-mate, living in a cottage on the hill, built by students and termed "University Grove." In this cottage was established the boarding-club, known later and appropriately as " The Struggle for Existence," and in later and more economical times as the " Strug." For a time, Dudley paid his way by rising at four o'clockto milk cows at the farm. Later he was made botanical collector, and this congenial .work he kept up until he became my successor as instructor in botany. In college Dudley was a member of the Delta Upsilon fraternity, and took an active part in holding this society to the high ideals (dikaia upotheke) on which it was originally based. He was also a charter member in the honorary scientific society of Sigma Xi (spoudon xunones).
In 1871 I went with him to his home at North Guilford, and I remember that his practical father said to me: 'There comes Willie across the fields with his hands full of flowers, just as he used to. I wonder if there is any way he can make a living by it.
Dudley graduated from Cornell in 1874, with the degree of B.S. In 1876, he received the degree of M.S., after which he spent some time in botanical study in Strassburg and Berlin. From 1872 to 1876 he was instructor in botany at Cornell, his eminent knowledge of the eastern flora overbalancing the fact that at first he had not yet received a degree. From 1876 to 1892 he was assistant professor of botany at Cornell, with a year's absence in 1880, in which he served as acting professor of biology in the University of Indiana, in the absence of the present writer, who then held that chair.
In 1892, Professor Dudley became professor of systematic botany at Stanford University, which position he held until, in January, 1911, failing health caused his retirement on the Carnegie Foundation as professor emeritus, his work being then taken by one of his students, Associate Professor Le Roy Abrams. Many of the leading botanists of the country have been students of Professor Dudley. H. E. Copeland, Kellerman, Lazenby, Branner were among his associates at Cornell. Atkins became his successor at Cornell. Abrams, Cook, Elmer, Olssen-Seffer, Cannon, Wight, E. B. Copeland, E. G. Dudley, Greeley, Herre, McMurphy and many others were under his tutelage at Stanford.
In Stanford University, Dudley was one of the most respected as well as best beloved members of the faculty. No one could come near to him without recognizing the extreme refinement of his nature; a keen intellect, an untiring joy in his chosen work, and the Puritan conscience at its best, with clear perceptions of his own duties to himself and a generous recognition of the rights and the aspirations of others.
Dudley entered with great joy into the study of the California flora. He became especially interested in the study of trees, the evolutionary relations of forms and especially the problems of geographical distribution. The conifers of California were his special delight, and he made many field trips with his students to all parts of the state, notably to the Sierra Nevada and the Sierra Santa Lucia. His extended collections were presented to Stanford University, where with the collections of Dr. Abrams they form the major part of the large" Dudley Herbarium."
A genus of stone-crops, of many species, abounding on the cliffs of California and especially on those which overhang the sea, was named Dudleay by Britton and Rose. Dudley pulverulenta is one of the most conspicuous plants in California wherever "sea and mountains meet."
Dudley was instrumental in inducing the state of California to purchase a forest of redwoods (Sequoia sempervirens), that this, the second of California's giant trees, might be preserved in a state of nature. Two thousand five hundred acres in the "Big Basin" of Santa Cruz County were thus bought and established as the "Sempervirens Park." For several years Dudley served on the board of control of this park.
Of the Sierra Club of California, Dudley was a leading member and for some years a director.
As an investigator, Professor Dudley was persistent and accurate, doing his work for the love of it. A partial list of his papers is given below. A large work on the conifers of the west was long projected, but still exists only in uncompleted manuscript.
Dudley was master of a quiet and refined but effective English style. He was one of thpse scientific men, too few I fear, who have real love for literature, and who understand what poetry is and what it is about. In his early days he wrote graceful verse.
Professor Dudley's health was good until about three years ago, when he set out to study the trees of Persia. In Egypt he was attacked by a severe cold or bronchitis which ended in tuberculosis.
He was never, married.
Scope and Content
Papers include field notes, a diary, manuscripts, articles and reprints, maps, and correspondence; most of the field notes relate to California, with occasional later annotations by other botanists. Some of the material relates to Big Basin Redwoods State Park and the Sierra Club. The diary is from a tour of the California missions from December 27, 1895 to January 7, 1896 and includes photographs. Correspondents include Michael Schuck Bebb, Frederick V. Coville, Elias Durand, Alice Eastwood, Gifford Pinchot, C. O. Thurston, Charles Frederick Millspaugh, Charles Sprague Sargent, and J. H. B. Pilkington. There is also a large correspondence file on California forest fires of 1899.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in six series: Series 1: General Correspondence; Series 2: Subject Files Series; 3: Biographical and Personal Papers; Series 4: Class materials, lecture notes, and manuscript articles; Series 5: Field Notes and Research Notes Series 6: Oversize publications and maps.
PARTIAL BIBLIOGRAPHY, OF THE BOTANICAL WRITINGS OF WILLIAM: RUSSELL DUDLEY
1. An Abnomlal Orchid. Abstract from the Proc. of the Amer. Ass'n. for the Adv. of Sci., Vol. 32, August, 1883.
2. Another Disease of the Strawberry. December, 1889.
3. Big Basin Redwood Park. Forester, July, 1901, 7: 157.
4. The Big Trees of California. Forester, September, 1900.
5. The Cayuga Flora. Bull. of Cornell Univ., 1886.
6. Charles Christopher Frost. Jr. Of Mycology, Vol. 2, 10 (October, 1886).
7. The Clover Rust. December, 1890.
8. Concerning the Vitality of Sequoia sempervirens. Palo Alto Times, March 17, 1908.
9. The Death of Dr. DeBary. Bot. Gaz., Vol.13: 64.
10. Directions for Laboratory Study. Anatomy and Histology of Plants. Cornell Univ., 1887.
11 Elias Magnus Fries. Jr. of Mycology, Vol. 2, August, 1886.
12. First Steps in the Study of Botany. The Educationist, Vol. 2, July, 1880.
13. Flora of the Lackawanna and Wyoming Valleys, 1892. (With Charles O. Thurston.)
14. Forestry Notes. Sierra Club Bull., 1901-02.
15. Forestry Notes. Sierra Club Bull., January, June, 1902-4: 71-14; (173-76).
10. Forestry Notes. Sierra Club Bull., June, 1903-4: 71,173, 246, 319.
17. Forestry Notes. Sierra Club Bull., January,1904-5: 82-85.
18. Forestry Notes. Sierra Club Bull., January,1905-5: 265-70.
19. Forestry Notes. Sierra Club Bull., 1905-1906.
20. Forestry Notes. Sierra Club Bull., June, 1908-6: 334-36.
21. The Geuus Phyllospadix, Wilder quarter Ceutury Book, Ithaca, N. Y., 1893.
22. The Hollyhock Rust. December, 1890.
23. A Laboratory Manual of Plant Histology. Crawfordsville, Ind. (1894). (With M. B. Thomas.)
24. Leafy Berries in Mitchella repens. Bull. of the Torrey Bot. Club, January, 1883, Vol.10: 1.
25. Lumbering in the Sequoia National Park. The Forester, December (1900).
26. Near the Kern's Grand Canon. Sierra Club Bull., June, 1903, Vol. 4: 301-07.
27. A Notable California Fir, Abies venusta. Forestry and Irrigation, May, 1902, Vol.8: 193.
28. The Onion Mold. December, 1889.
29. Phyllospadix. Its Systematic Characters and Distribution. Extract from Zoe., February 26, 1894.
30. A preliminary List of the Vascular Plants of the Lackawanna anc1 Wyoming Valleys. In Lackawanna Institute of History and Science, Proc. & Coll., Vol. 1: 29.
31. Report of the Cryptogamic Botanist.
32. Sketch of Curtis. Jr. of Mycology, May 1886, Vol. 2: 5.
33. Strassburg and its Botanical Laboratory. Bot. Gaz., December, 1888, Vol. 13: 305.
34. The Strawyberry Leaf-blight.
35. Trees along the Tulare Trails. Sierra Club Bull., June, 1902 (Vol. 4: 153- 56).
36. The Vitality of Sequoia gigantea. Read before the Alumni Association of Columbia University, January, 1905.
37. Zonal distribution of trees and shrubs in the Southern Sierra. Sierra Club Bull., June, 1901, 3: 298-31 2.
Stanford University -- Faculty.; Botany -- United States -- History.; Botany -- United States.; Dudley, William Russel; Dudley, William Russel
- General Correspondence
  - Abrams, Leroy, 1909 and undated, 1909 & undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anthony, A. W., 1896-98, 1896-1898 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Applegate, Elmer, 1894-1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A, 1888-1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beeb, M.S., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brandegee, Katherine, 1892-1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Branner, John C, 1886/1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bray, William L., 1892-1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Britton, N. L., 1889-1902 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - B, 1881-1904 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Campbell, Douglas, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Congdon, J. W., 1895-1900 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cook, Mel T., 1894-1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Coville, Frederick V., 1889-1905 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cusick, Wm. C., 1887-1898 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Curtiss, A. H., 1882-1896 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - C, 1889-1902 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Congdon, J. W. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Davis, R. N., 1886-1892 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Davy, J. Burtt, 1893-1896 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dudley family (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Durand, Elias, 1893-1897 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - D., 1887-1904 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Eastwood, Alice, 1893-1910 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Elmer, A. D. E., 1899-1908 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - E., 1886-1902 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence regarding 1899 forest fires, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fitch, Mrs. D. B., 1889-1893 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - French, Edward L., 1883 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Graves, W. R., 1889-1892 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - F-G, 1883-1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hansen, George, 1894-1897 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Heller, A. A., 1894-1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hough, Romeyn B., 1890-1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - H., 1882-1910 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jordan, David Starr, 1886-1908 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - J., 1882-1904 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - K., 1889-1903 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lazenby, William R., 1880-1883 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lemmon, J. G., 1881-1908 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - L, 1893-1904 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Martindale, Isaac and Elizabeth J., 1891/1893 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Millspaugh, Charles F., 1886-1888 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mohr, Charles, 1894-1899 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - M, 1881-1904 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - N, 1894-1904 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - O, 1887-1905 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Parish, Samuel B., 1893-1902 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1899-1902 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Porter, Thomas C., 1886-1889 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Price, W. W., 1894 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Pringle, C. G., 1883-1902 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - P, 1884-1899 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Robinson, Benjamin L., 1892-1901 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - R, 1885-1910 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Sargent, C. S., 1886-1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Schofield, E. H., 1896-1897 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Stanford University notices, request for information, reports, forms, etc., 1895-1910 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - S, 1879-1904 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Thomas, Mason B., 1894-1899 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Thurston, C. 0., 1891-1898 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Trelease, William, 1887-1896 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - T, 1883-1897 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Underwood, Lucien M., 1896-1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - U.S.D.A., correspondence, 1891-1907 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - U.S.D.A., form letters, service orders, etc., 1901-1907 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - V-W, 1885-1902 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Yatabe, R., 1890 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters, unreadable names, and fragment of a letter dated June 21,1887 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing letters (with no incoming), 1887-1910 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stamps [empty envelopes addressed to Dudley] (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (not by or to Dudley), 1869-1910 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Subject Files
  - Asa Gray, notes on (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Big Basin Maps -1904 and undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Big Basin miscellaneous (mostly notes, lists, with one typed summary) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Big Basin legal documents, 1902-1904 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Big Basin, Dudley's article in Stanford Sequoia, April 16, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Bureau of Forestry and related correspondence, 1897-1902 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Calaveras Groves of Big Trees: Draft of statement/report/letter re national (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - California Redwood Park Commission correspondence, 1900-1901 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - California Redwood Park Commission correspondence, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - California Redwood Park Commission correspondence, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - California Redwood Park Commission correspondence, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - California Redwood Park Commission correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - California Redwood Park Commission minutes, 1901-1902 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - California Redwood Park Commission minutes, 1902-1903 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - California Redwood Park Commission minutes, 1903-1904 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - California Redwood Park Commission minutes, 1905-1906 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - California Redwood Park Commission: 1. H. B. Pilkington, 1903-1910 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - California Redwood Park Commission: Check book and receipts, 1903-1906 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Cornell University: botany lab instructions 1882; completed forms re fungus problems, 1888; Fourth Annual Report of the ... New York State College of Forestry at Cornell University, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Field notes of meanders of creeks in the Big Basin, Santa Cruz and San Mateo Counties, surveyed by E. D. Perry, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - " The Flora of Ithaca, New York. A thesis in botany present to the faculty and trustees of Cornell University for the degree of Master of Science by William Russell Dudley, June 1876 " - mss list of flora and general description text (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Forest Reserve Manual, Dept. of the Interior, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Handbook of Plant Geography (Working Disposition of) by Dudley and Olsson-Seffer, with cover letter from Olsson-Seffer [originals were damaged from water and possibly vermin; acid-free photocopies were made and originals discarded] (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hetch-Hetchy: draft letter against the dam, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Litchfield flora [portion of printed book] circa 1822 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - LSJU Botany graduates list, 1892-1911 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - LSJU Class books, 1893-1911 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - LSJU communications: bound volume with letters, notes, notices and some blank forms 1893-95 [items are pasted over original notes from a Philosophy of History class, 1874], 1893-1895 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - LSJU: Harvey Herbarium, letters and list, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - LSJU: Herbarium reports [includes one by Per Olsson-Seffer 1904] and lists, 1904 and undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Biographical and Personal Papers
  - LSJU: Herbarium reports and lists [includes plants collected at Lake Maxinkuckee, IN, by B. W. Evermann 1900-01], 1897-1908 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - LSJU: Natural History Museum and Dudley Herbarium [plans and misc. correspondence], 1924-32 and undated, 1924-32/undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - LSJU notices (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous financial records, 1894-1906 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Notes on the Reproduction of Douglas Spruce," by William F. Wight, with a chart (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photographs: Earle Hall at Columbia University; plant (F. L. Clarke) taken without lens on plate (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Primary List of Plants Used in Medicine in the U.S. from the U. S. Dispensatory, edition of 1884 (handwritten list), and USDA and Smithsonian forms on medicinal plants, 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Recommendations concerning the Forest belonging to the Pacific Improvement Company at Monterey, with cover letter, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Report on the condition of the Pacific Improvement Company's forest of Monterey Pines and Monterey Cypress at Pacific Grove, Cal. With special reference to injuries by insects and fungus diseases and recommendations for treatment. By Geo. A. Coleman, Forester and Entomologist." typescript (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Santa Clara Valley, Native trees suitable for planting, 1902 (includes 2 letters) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Sierra Club, 1893-1902 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Unitarian Church, Ithaca, pledges to payoff debt, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Visalia Board of Trade: invitation to visit Mount Whitney, 1900, and related correspondence 1900-02, 1900-1902 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Address books (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Diary re trip to see several California missions, 1895-96 [original bound typescript with photographs], 1895-1896 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Diary 1895-96 [carbon copy; bound typescript with photographs], 1895-1896 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Diary 1895-96 [second carbon copy; bound typescript with photographs], 1895-1896 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Poetry and prose manuscript volume, 1864-1874 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Membership certificates, 1893-1896 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Plant specimen cards, W. R. Dudley, collector (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Travel ephemera 1890-1905 and undated, 1890-1905/undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Biographical articles, including Science, N.S., Vol. XXXIV, No. 866, August 4, 1911; "Professor Dudley's Work at Stanford," by Leroy Abrams, 1911; and the memorial address by Douglas H. Campbell,1913, 1911/1913 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Issues of the Daily Palo Alto with articles about Dudley and other clippings, 1901-1912 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Assorted notices from organizations, etc. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Partial bibliography (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Cayuga Flora, Bulletin of Cornell University, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Directions for Laboratory Study Anatomy and Histology of Plants, Cornell University, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - A Preliminary List of the Vascular Plants of Lackawanna and Wyoming Valleys [1887] (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - A Preliminary List of the Vascular Plants of Lackawanna and Wyoming Valleys [1887] (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Flora of Lackawanna and Wyoming Valleys, 1892 with supplement, 1895, 1892/1895 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Genus Phyllospadix, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Phyllospadix, Its Systematic Characters and Distribution, Zoe, Vol.lV, No. 4, 1894 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sierra Club Bulletin (report on Sierra Forest Reservation), 1896 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - A Short Account of the Big Tress of California, USDA Division of Forestry, Bulletin No. 28, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Lumbering in Sequoia National Park," The Forester, December 1900 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Zonal Distribution of Trees and Shrubs in the Southern Sierra ", Sierra Club Bulletin, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "A Notable California Fir," Forestry & Irrigation, May 1902 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Vitality of Sequoia Gigantea, published version of lecture before Columbia college alumni, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Assorted reprints, 1883-1912 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Sierra Club Bulletin articles by Dudley (photocopies) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Publications by others (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Assorted botanical publications, 1838-1902 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Assorted botanical publications, 1877-1909 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Assorted book notices and study announcements (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Plant catalogs (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Plant print lists (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Class materials, lecture notes, and manuscript articles
  - Histologyll-lecture notes, outlines 1885-1891 and undated, 1885-1891/undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Histology/2 - lecture notes, outlines, 1885-1889 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Histology/3 -lecture notes, outlines, 1886-1889 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Geographic Distribution course, materials for (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Geographic Distribution, Lecture III (with earlier notes), 1910 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Geographic Distribution exam (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Plant distribution, general - map (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Notes for lecture on utility of forests and forest botany, May 3, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Notes for a lecture on geographical distribution of plants, given at Scanton, PA, June 1886 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Lecture on flowers for Elementary Botany (with later notes), 1897 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Notes for lecture on trees and lecture on ferns, 1889 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Lecture notes: the floral realms (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Lecture notes: distribution of animal and plant life, May 8 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Lecture notes: September 24, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Address to Pacific States Floral Congress (ms and typescript), 1901 (Box 9, Folder 5)